Soviet Union and Russia Seventh Day Adventist Subject Files, Inclusive Dates: 1925-2005, undated, Bulk: 1975-1981
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union and Russia Seventh Day Adventist Subject Files
Inclusive Dates: 1925-2005, undated, Bulk: 1975-1981
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
26
Keston Institute, 1969 -
6 A4 document boxes
The Soviet Union and Russia Seventh Day Adventist Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the Seventh Day Adventist Church and persecution of Seventh Day Adventists in the former Soviet Union.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
In the early 1970s, Keston began collecting materials on the persecution of Seventh Day Adventists in the Soviet Union.
Seventh Day Adventist churches emerged in Eastern Europe in the 1880s. In Russia, the first Adventist converts appeared among German settlers on the Volga and in Ukraine. In 1886, well-known preacher Ludwig Richard Conradi helped begin the first Russian Adventist church in a German community in Crimea. The Tsarist government tolerated Adventist believers because they were not of Russian nationality, remained confined to their communities, and did not pose a threat to the Orthodox Church. As more Russians began sympathizing with Adventists, authorities subjected members of the “German sect” to censorship and surveillance. Conversion of Russian nationals to Adventism became illegal and punishable by arrest, interrogation, imprisonment, and/or exile.
The situation improved in 1905 after events forced Tsar Nicholas II to form a constitutional monarchy. The constitution granted civil rights to Protestant denominations and legalized conversion from Orthodoxy to other religious creeds. In 1906, the Seventh Day Adventist Church received official recognition. Adventists began publishing religious literature, which previously has been supplied from abroad. By 1914, the number of Adventists in the Russian Empire more than doubled.
The outbreak of the First World War presented Russian Adventists with many challenges, including increased hostility from authorities because of the faith’s German origin and believers’ refusal to bear arms. A disagreement over the latter contributed to a split in the Russian Adventist Church and led to creation of the True and Free Adventist Church in the late 1920s. During the First World War, a number of Adventist ministers and elders were exiled to the inner areas of the Russian Empire because of their evangelical activities. Conscientious objectors were persecuted and sent to prison camps. Survivors were freed by the Bolsheviks after the 1917 Revolution.
In an attempt to eradicate the Russian Orthodox Church which was considered their main ideological enemy, the Bolsheviks tried to gain support of Protestant denominations. During a short period of tolerance, Russian Adventists received exemptions from military service, established collective communes, openly evangelized, held religious classes, and published literature. The Russian division of the Seventh Day Adventist Church became the All-Union Council of Seventh Day Adventists. However, Soviet authorities prevented Russian representatives from participating in international meetings.
Tolerance ended with the 1929 Law on Religious Cults, which restricted evangelization and religious education of children, imposed registration requirements on congregations, and encouraged service in the army. During the ensuing years, authorities arrested Adventist church leaders and sent them to labor camps, limited religious activities to church services on registered premises, closed churches, and banned publications.
In 1928, a split within the official Russian Adventist Church resulted in creation of True and Free Seventh Day Adventists, an underground organization. Both registered and unregistered Adventists existed until 1960. At the beginning of Nikita Khrushchev’s anti-religious campaign, Soviet authorities abolished the official All-Union Council of Seventh Day Adventists, deprived the registered Adventists of centralized leadership, and nationalized all church property.
The unofficial True and Free Seventh Day Adventists publicized the situation in the Soviet Union in the 1970s. They reached out to the international religious community during the 1978 Madrid Conference with documentation on Soviet state persecution. Their witness drew passionate support of Soviet dissidents of various denominations, including Aleksandr Ginsburg and Andrei Sakharov. Unfortunately, the lack of attention from official Adventists abroad discouraged True and Free Adventists from openly joining the religious dissent movement. Vladimir Shelkov, the most prominent leader of the True and Free Seventh Day Adventists, spent 26 years in Soviet gulags. He died in prison in 1980 at the age of 84.
Registered Adventists openly rejected True and Free Adventists claims of state religious persecution. Because of the registered Adventists’ position, Soviet authorities lessened restrictions on the official Adventist Church in the 1970s by allowing publication of a monthly journal and limited religious literature, including articles by Helen White and sermons on peace. Soviet Adventist contact with Adventists abroad strengthened during the 1980s. Russian Adventist Church representatives began attending international conferences and hosted foreign delegations. In 1990, the Russian Adventist Church, under the leadership of Mikhail Kulakov, received official state registration and became an East-European Division of the General Conference of Seventh Day Adventists.
The Russian Seventh Day Adventist Church celebrated its 100th Anniversary in the 1980’s, officially founded Zaoksky Adventist University in 1988, and established a publishing house in the Tula Region in 1995. The denomination maintains active membership in the International Association for Religious Freedom.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union and Russia Seventh Day Adventist Subject Files contain materials about the history of the Seventh Day Adventist Church and persecution of its members in the Soviet Union. The files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, transcripts, reports, and various forms of Samizdat, including underground publications and unofficially circulated documents and records.
The materials cover a period from 1928 to 2005, with the bulk from 1975 to 1981. The most notable topics include, but are not limited to, state authorities’ oppressive practices against True and Free Seventh Day Adventists and their fight against state atheism for the right to religious freedom and conscientious objection. Individual accounts of persecution include the trials of Adventist minister and activist Vladimir Shelkov in Tashkent, Uzbek SSR, and of Adventist believers in Stavropol’skii Krai.
Some materials pertain to relations between the Seventh Day Adventist Church and the state in post-Soviet Russia.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received most of the Soviet Union and Russia Seventh Day Adventist materials in files organized by subject. This original filing system has been largely preserved.
The Soviet Union and Russia Seventh Day Adventist Subject Files are currently arranged into two series: I. General and II. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 26.
Related Resources
Related references
Bourdeaux, Michael., and S. B. Filatov. Sovremennai︠a︡ religioznai︠a︡ zhizn)' Rossii: opyt sistematicheskogo opisanii︠a︡. Moskva: Logos, 2003.
Sapiets, Marite. “One hundred years of Adventism in Russia and the Soviet Union.” Religion, State, and Society vol. 12, no. 3 (1984): 256-273.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Shelkov, Vladimir.
Places
Soviet Union -- Church history.; Soviet Union -- Politics and Government.
Subjects
Civil rights -- Soviet Union.; Conscientious objectors -- Soviet Union.; Freedom of religion -- Soviet Union.; Human rights -- Soviet Union.; Seventh-Day Adventists -- Soviet Union.; Trials (Political crimes and offenses).; Underground Literature -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Transcripts.
- General, 1925-2005, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains information on the history and persecution of the Seventh Day Adventist Church in the Soviet Union, including oppressive practices against Adventists and their fight for the right to religious freedom and conscientious objection.
  - Seventh Day Adventist Church. General (1 of 2), 1925, 1953-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Seventh Day Adventist Church. General (2 of 2), 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Seventh Day Adventist Church. History. General, 1970-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Individual Adventist Believers, 1963, 1978, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Adventist Church Administration, 1978-1979, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adventist Church-State Relations, 1975-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General, 1967, 1976-1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Harassment, 1975-1980, 1988, 1996, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Physical Assault, 1977-1980, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Disruption of Meetings, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Fines, 1978-1979, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Interrogations, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials, 1974-1981, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Imprisonment, 1974-1981, 1986-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. State Interference in Church Affairs, 1978-1980, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Discrimination in Education, 1979, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Misuse of Psychiatry, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Attacks in the Media, 1962-1980, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. House Searches, 1975-1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Loss of Parental Rights, 1975-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Adventist Church Life, 1962, 1972, 1975-1979, 1987, 1989, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Adventist Church. Official Publications, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Adventist Church. Clergy and Priesthood, 1973, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Shelkov, Vladimir (1 of 2), 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Shelkov, Vladimir (2 of 2), 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Adventist Church. International Relations, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Adventist Believers. Defense of Adventist Believers Rights, 1977-1979, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Adventist Believers. Refusal to Do Military Service, 1976-1979, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Adventist Samizdat, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Adventist Church Theology, Philosophy, and Ethics, 1970, 1978-1979, 1987, 2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Adventist Church. Unity, Schisms and Doctrinal Differences, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Adventist Church. Statistics, 1921-1928, 1974-1975, 1979, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Adventist Church. Relations with Fellow Believers, 1977, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Adventist Church Relations with Other Denominations, 1976-1977, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Adventist Church Religion and National Identity, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bible, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Adventist Church. Children and Youth, 1963, 1969-1979, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Adventist Church. Sociology and Family, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Adventist Church. Post-Soviet Development. General, 1991, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Adventist Church Publications, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Samizdat, 1975-1994, undated; 2
  The series contains information on the persecution of True and Free Seventh Day Adventist believers in the Soviet Union and their fight for the rights of conscientious objection and emigration on religious grounds. The materials include unofficially circulated documents, testimonials, reports, letters, and appeals.
  - Adventist Church Administration. All Union Council of True and Free Adventists (1 of 8), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Adventist Church Administration. All Union Council of True and Free Adventists (2 of 8), 1978 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Adventist Church Administration. All Union Council of True and Free Adventists (3 of 8), 1978 September (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Adventist Church Administration. All Union Council of True and Free Adventists (4 of 8), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Adventist Church Administration. All Union Council of True and Free Adventists (5 of 8), 1978 December (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Adventist Church Administration. All Union Council of True and Free Adventists (6 of 8), 1979 March (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Adventist Church Administration. All Union Council of True and Free Adventists (8 of 8), 1980 May (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Adventist Church Administration. All Union Council of True and Free Adventists (8 of 8), 1980 July (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Adventist Church-State Relations, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (1 of 9), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (2 of 9), 1977 June (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (3 of 9), 1977 June (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (4 of 9), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (5 of 9), 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (6 of 9), 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (7 of 9), 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (8 of 9), 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. General (9 of 9), 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Harassment, 1978, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Physical Assault, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Disruption of Meetings, 1977, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Fines, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Interrogation, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. General (1 of 2), 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. General (2 of 2), 1979 March-July (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. Stavropolskii Krai, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. Uzbek SSR (1 of 3), 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. Uzbek SSR (2 of 3), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. Uzbek SSR (3 of 3), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. Uzbek SSR. Testimonials (1 of 2), 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. Uzbek SSR. Testimonials (2 of 2), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Trials. Uzbek SSR. Buryat Republic, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Imprisonment. General (1 of 2), 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Imprisonment. General (2 of 2), 1978-1980, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Discrimination in Education, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Misuse of Psychiatry (1 of 3), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Misuse of Psychiatry (2 of 3), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Misuse of Psychiatry (3 of 3), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Attacks in the Media, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. House Searches. Confiscation of Property (1 of 2), 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. House Searches. Confiscation of Property (2 of 2), 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Oppressive Practices against Adventist Believers. Loss of Parental Rights, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Shelkov, Vladimir (1 of 3), 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Shelkov, Vladimir (2 of 3), 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Shelkov, Vladimir (3 of 3), 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Shelkov, Vladimir. Writings, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Galetsky, Rostislav, 1977, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Murkin, Aleksei (1 of 2), 1983-1984, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Individual Adventist Clergy. Murkin, Aleksei (2 of 2), 1983-1984, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Adventist Church Contacts with International Organizations, 1975, 197901980 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Group for Legal Struggle, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (1 of 10), ca. 1975 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (2 of 10), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (3 of 10), undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (4 of 10), 1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (5 of 10), 1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (6 of 10), 1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (7 of 10), 1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (8 of 10), 1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (9 of 10), 1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Defense of Adventist Believers' Rights. The Legal Fight for Rights against the Dictatorship of State Atheism (10 of 10), 1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Adventist Church. Visual Materials, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)